There's a lesson in marketing and sales,
and actually in business, that we can take
from boxing. Now, I am not a boxer,
although I'd like to think
I have a left, right,
good night in the tank.
I'm actually a brown belt in Brazilian
jujitsu, so I'm anything but good at
striking. But there's a lesson in here,
and if you let me teach it to you, all of
your strategy on social media will not
just perform better, it will give you a
better understanding of what you should be
doing on a daily basis.
This is a punch bag.
I'm not actually going to use these wraps.
Just putting them away, set the scene.
If any of you out there
are competent boxers,
please forgive me for what I'm about
to do. In boxing, we have a jab. Now,
the jab isn't really ever going to knock
anyone out,
so people therefore think it's not a good
punch.
When people get into a street fight,
you can tell how much fighting experience
they
have with which punch they throw first.
Most dudes think, "Right, this
is my knockout hand.
They're getting it straight away." It's
probably the most predictable punch ever
to
see coming in a fight.
They come walking in.
But the jab is often what sets up the
cross.
The jab is what sets up the hook.
The jab is what sets
up everything.
So the jab isn't used to knock people out,
although it can happen
rarely.
The jab is used primarily to set up what
is to come.
The jab represents things we do on social
media and in content creation
where we are trying to set someone up.
Now, we're not trying to hurt them,
we're not trying to stun them.
What we're trying to do
is to have something as a prerequisite to
the thing we
actually want to throw, which
is a call to action in content.
We could argue that
if I try a call to action
too soon in a fight, it's too predictable.
We've not buttered them up at all.
The main strategy
that we want in social media
is to accrue goodwill.
And the way we accrue goodwill
is through jabbing.
It's through putting out loads of bits of
content, whether it's Reels, YouTube
videos, blogs, emails, whatever it is.
We want to keep jabbing,
and the more we jab, the better we
are setting up the
right hook.
So many people on social media,
the second they start, they start
throwing rights.
And the rights aren't getting through,
and they start to think,
"Oh, maybe it's the punch.
Maybe it's the way I'm throwing it.
Maybe I need to go for an overhand." It's
not.
It's the fact you're not setting up your
content well enough.
Most competent boxers before any fight
will have their guard up.
Everyone on social media
is doing the same.
They know you are trying to sell them
something.
Similar to when someone comes into the
duty free when you're looking at
aftershave.
"Can I help?" "No,
thanks." We say no thanks,
even though we do want aftershave or
perfume.
That's why we're in duty free in the first
place.
Truth be told, if we
were to find a scent and we loved it
and we vibed with it and
went, "Oh my god,
that's amazing," we're walking out with
it.
But our first reaction
when someone says to come and assist us,
we're like, "No
thanks.
Leave me alone." That's what the majority
of people are doing to you in the
world of social media.
They potentially do want what you're
selling, but you're
going to have to do some convincing first.
Me when it comes to fighting, Declan.
Street fights especially.
It's good to throw a combination
that people can't
defend. You ready?
[punching bag] Can't defend it.
Two punches, one kick.
You ever seen someone defend that?
Of course you haven't. It's Wing Chun.
Know Wing Chun? I don't want any trouble.
I don't want any trouble.
I don't want troub- [punching bag]
That could kill a man. Do you know what?
Maybe don't put that near the internet.
All right.
That is assault with a deadly weapon with
intent. That.
One more time. What's your frame rate at?
Is it going to capture it? Oh, yeah.
You sure? Oh, yeah. Yeah. Look,
if you need to change the frame rate
because- Don't
worry, mate. You're all right. Oh,
I'm just gonna... [punching bag] Done.
Let's go back upstairs.
I know it can sometimes seem like I
continue to repeat
myself in videos,
but I like to remind you
that this isn't always about educating
people, it's about reminding people.
There might be things that you know,
but you need to be reminded to actually do
it,
like some of you still don't have an email
list even though for literally years,
what, 2018? I've been telling people,
"You need an email list." There's a
four-stage system in
which we must take this principle of the
jab, jab,
right hook and apply it. So stage one,
social media, brand
awareness, et cetera.
One of the reasons
that I love a hybrid model for a lot of
coaches to be doing some in-person
and some online is
that it gives you a lot more
patience to build and curate an audience.
Similar to farming.
When it comes to farming, most fa-- Again,
you can tell, I don't know much about
boxing and I don't know much about
farming.
But I've watched three seasons of
"Clarkson's Farm" so let's get into it.
We must plant the seeds,
allow the crops to flourish, and then we
must harvest the acres of the crops.
Farmers will wait nine months to a year to
do so, yet you think,
"I've been posting for three weeks on
social media.
Why haven't they bought my stuff yet?" We
must have a patient approach to it.
So what I would say in the onset
is to just focus on accruing goodwill
by putting out jabs.
I want people to be watching your content
going, "Oh my God,
this is so good. This should be illegal,
this is so good.
Why isn't this person even asking me for
money?
Why isn't this person trying to sell to
me?" Back in the day, I used to be a dirty
dog,
and this was my system for getting laid.
If, as a gentleman on the first date,
I try and sleep with a woman, that can set
me back four dates, sometimes five.
A true gentleman doesn't try
and sleep with a lady on the first date
because he
knows if he's not too pushy,
if he's genuinely there to make a
connection, to
get to know someone,
to get to share his energy with
that woman,
then maybe he could get the [whistles] on
date two or three. What am I saying?
I'm saying if you
are too pushy in the onset, you
are pushing the sale further down
the line.
By being less pushy in the onset
and focusing more solely on
give, give, give, give,
when it comes to take,
you will perform a lot better
and it will work a lot better for you.
And if I'm going to share business advice,
I might as well share personal advice.
Sometimes as a gentleman, you do try
and abstain from trying to sleep with
someone
on the first date,
but human nature can get the better of
you.
So I would only recommend attending
that first date without a loaded gun,
if you gentlemen know what I'm saying.
But don't
too close to a date,
because then you have a high chance of
canceling it.
Everyone knows what it's like.
It's 2:00 PM, you think,
"I've got a date tonight.
I'll just have a little tommy tank." Neck
minute, 3:30, you're having an afternoon
nap going,
"I'm not even interested in going on
that date tonight." Could play Call
of Duty: Warzone instead with the boys,
and that explains the majority of my 20s.
Anyway, where were we? Stage two.
The call to action that primarily all of
us want to be using in stage one social
media brand awareness is to get someone's
contact information.
The best contact information we want from
them is probably
going to be email marketing.
So it's a shame for us to do all of these
jabs
to then come in with a bad hook.
So we need to ensure for that
hook to land on the chin correctly,
that we are offering value with those
emails. It isn't enough to just say,
"Please join my newsletter." There's a
principle we know called WIIFM,
what's in it for me?
We must play into that WIIFM.
Good friend of mine, Lucy Lord,
on Instagram
has 150,000 followers.
Very good friend of mine
and an even better baker.
We're talking this morning.
She's saying to me,
"I'm not sure about my product, my
offer,
what I'm going to sell in 2025." I'm like,
"Hold on.
Before we worry about that,
the actionable task we should be doing now
is growing
your email list.
So we need to start putting out content."
I said, "What are you
going to give people for their email
address?" She goes, "I
was thinking of giving
them some free recipes." I was like,
"Come on.
It's 2025 and you're trying to give people
free recipes?" A recipe is just the
combination of food
that you've put together to make a meal.
The fact people buy recipes blows my
flipping mind.
If you were to ask me the question,
"James, do you want some free?" "No,
I don't
want free recipes." I said to her,
"Let's work back from real problems
that people
are facing in your audience." I said,
"Look, you have a primarily
cooking-based business.
The majority of people probably like
following you
and watching your content of the recipes,
not because they're planning on making
them, but they like watching
that food get created." They like the food
porn
of seeing that chocolate brownie
or those air fryer roast potatoes
or that whatever it is.
People just enjoy seeing food made well.
Me, when I'm feeding my baby,
sometimes I'll put on something of someone
cooking a
tomahawk steak, and
when they cut through the steak at the end
and they squeeze it,
I'm like, "Oh my God.
That's amazing." I said to Lucy,
"How about this as part of
your email autoresponder series?
Why not tell people what the settings on
the oven do, what trays they need, what
papers they use for baking,
what temperatures
are good to cook things at?
Do they need a stainless pan?
Do they use Teflon?" All the things
that I don't
know. Instead,
why not make your email series something
that can break down every
single barrier someone has between just
watching your recipes and actually taking
part in them.
Don't give them free recipes.
Give them the tools to bring them closer
to cooking or baking for the first time.
Because Declan,
have you ever baked a brownie? Exactly.
I don't bake.
I'm rubbish at cooking. But if you
were to empower me with the tools to
understand
things,
I could then go into the kitchen and go,
"Babe, want me to preheat the
oven to 200 on the fan setting?" She'd go,
"Oh my God.
How'd you know that
was a fan setting?" "Oh,
I've been reading Lucy Lord's emails.
They've been telling me
that I need to be using this paper," blah,
blah, blah,
whatever. Then before you know it,
I'm 11 emails deep into a free newsletter
that I
only joined to get the information away
from Lucy, and I'm now thinking for my
girlfriend's birthday,
I might bake her some brownies.
Those emails could pertain such value
that it could influence my habits of the
way that I perceive my life
and who I am and what I can do as a
person.
The next thing you know,
I'm in the kitchen cooking.
Suddenly, when it's someone's birthday
or someone's leaving a work thing or
whatever it is,
I'm now a different person.
Instead of shopping Amazon,
I'm thinking about what things I could
bake for someone
or cook for someone or make for someone.
Actually, case in point,
I went down a rabbit hole of watching a
video of how to
cook the perfect steak.
And let's just say
that the steaks I've been cooking at
home are so good
that even my missus' parents came around
and entrusted me in
doing the steaks on the barbie.
There's a system,
but I'll tell you another time.
So what I'm saying is socials, yes, jab,
jab, right hook, but if you
want to make that right hook be as
effective as possible, make sure
that your call
to action isn't a give, give, give.
It's a, "Let me give you some more value,
but the place I'm going to give you that
value is in the form of email marketing
where I can have a conversation with you."
Because similar to getting laid,
trying to have that conversation with
someone on
social media is like a dance floor.
People are with their friends.
The music's really loud.
[imitates dance music] "Hey, where
are you from?
Do you want to get a drink sometime?"
Whereas when we can take that conversation
and bring it to email marketing,
it's opposite, one-on-one, quiet room,
lovely setting.
We hit the value in the emails because
those jabs don't stop.
It is jab, jab, give me your email. Email,
email, email, email.
Some people might need to be jabbed for 10
months before they buy your product.
Then the call to action,
which should be in every email,
is visit my landing page
or my sales page.
We can't just make it all about buying the
product at stage one or stage two.
Stage three, we're still
not there saying,
"Give me your money." Stage three,
we still need to jab them a
little bit more.
These jabs can be a bit more accurate.
What it is, why they need it,
what they get, how much it costs,
why to trust you.
They're the five stages
that need to be on any sales page and in
your sales video.
Then the final right hook at the end,
buy now. Not a sales call. At this point,
you have set people up for
success. Content, accruing goodwill,
changing the way people see about
things,
being an all-round good cunt on social
media.
Boom, give me your email address. Email,
value, value,
value. Mindset perspective.
Change of thought. Boom.
Visit my landing page. Landing page.
What it is, more about the product,
what they get, how much it costs,
why it costs
that much, why they should trust you.
Here's some testimonials.
Here's a money-back guarantee.
Fucking give me your money, cunt.
It shouldn't really be that.
It should be buy now. They're the stages.
There needs to be combinations that
are set in place between the beginning of
the
journey and back down.
Because the majority of people
are just running in with this
massive haymaker going, "Buy my shit."
And people are like,
"Fuck off, mate." Whack. And
if you can follow that structure,
honestly,
it will give you so much more to do on
social media.
For instance,
this video has no call to actions in.
No please click my link in the
description.
Well,
there's a bit of reverse psychology there,
Declan.
They might end up going to the link in the
description.
In fact, I'm just jabbing, jabbing.
I'm walking away, walking away.
Don't need to be throwing this bad boy
today. It's done enough damage.
But talking of damage,
if you like this video,
you'll absolutely love this one.
And I'll tell you what,
what you're supposed to do on YouTube
is have an
introduction and a hook to your video.
You have some kind of setup.
You have some kind of payoff.
Then at the end of the video,
you're supposed to open
a new hook. Wouldn't it be interesting
if the email marketing could be...
And then you're supposed to point to a
video that pays off that hook.
But what I do is I actually get YouTube to
recommend a video because rather
than me trying to create some complex
infrastructure of go to this video, go to
this video, go to...
I just point to what YouTube recommends
because chances are
it's a video you've not seen.
And I promise, if you do watch this one,
I won't
teach you anything about boxing.
So click that. Whack.